so unless you had a topic I thought of a
topic that might be very interesting to
you and me and also helpful to me so
it's something I might be able to use
and that is like this this thing I'm
trying to do the insight symposium we
can call it and the different ways that
people understand what this I call it
kalev insight work is so I'm trying to
use a term that can stand in for the
different types of methodologies people
have been using so I know Terry patent
he's got a book he calls it trans
rhetorical intersubjective practice then
they're circling and there's a
collective presence in this what RIA bet
calls it there you know I know that gtc
Terry o'fallon and gtc do transform a
transformative change but I don't think
they have a real specific term for the
group process a lot of people talk about
developing the wii space that's another
one years ago this predates most of most
of those people they talked about the
circle being they actually hypothesized
a new mind of a collective entity talked
about the circle being who did that
groups in Europe the no one really does
well there are some people still talk
about like that but that's not in
fashion that's more of a indigenous or
magical or kind of a more of a mythical
understanding so in Andrew Cohen's
evolutionary and
he does talk about he doesn't call it a
transpersonal field but he almost comes
close to talking about it a new cut type
of entity that arises a collective
entity so that would be probably the
closest to this and so in so what's
interesting in this work is that people
it's the work is at the point where
people are trying to make distinctions
and so I don't know if you've done a lot
of that work or you're interested in
that work but maybe just kind of
describe a little bit about how you
understand that work or what might be
interesting about it I know you're doing
more of an individual kind of journey
but um so that could be one thing we
could talk about to tell you the truth I
don't know that much about it myself you
know so but but I I um well let's start
with yeah I did why is it interesting to
you it's interesting to me for a couple
of reasons number one is because people
that I highly respect have talked about
it in ways that are important to me so
for example they'll say something really
new is happening but they're able to
make distinctions between those versions
of it that are not what they've
experienced and can tend to be confused
with what is a new experience so there's
like a pre trans kind of thing here
right and so in there's a lot of
confusion
around what this new capacity for being
together is now I have had I haven't
gotten to a lot of these experiences but
most of my experiences I would describe
as subtle energy fields right so subtle
energy could be even mass consciousness
is subtle energy or you know and I'm not
saying that these so I respect that
these people can make that distinction
that we're not talking about
fundamentalist Baptists having a unitive
experience is primarily a subtle energy
experience I mean that that's an
interesting experience because subtle
energy can transmit and you know you can
ride those waves and you could have mass
consciousness and so that's not a path
that interests me and I think a lot of
post-war humanists in the end
postmodernist in the new age thing
that's really what they're playing with
and not naming it correctly so you know
there's a long tradition of debunking
spiritual materialism and so for me just
now when this new other thing may be
arising it's important to me as I don't
know some kind of investigator you know
I don't know who pointed me the lead
examiner but the what it may it's
interesting to me to look at that from a
perspective of being able to make
valuable distinctions and and one of the
distinctions I think it matters is the
difference between a group experience
that's primed in such a way that there
is alignment around a conceptual object
that then gets us
associated with subtle energy field and
then becomes that group becomes
vulnerable to being distracted by the
SEC conceptual object so you could have
for example groups thinking that there
is a circle being or groups thinking
that there's an authentic self or not
you know and again distracted by the
conceptual object and the experience is
not remain at a prot as a practice now
Terry patents new work said a really a
lot of cool things so he said it's a
praxis you can't objectify it in and so
when I see people making those
distinctions and still believing in the
work or still going forward within the
work then I get more curious so that's
just a little bit of what I would talk
about now I've had experiences that I
would call collective insight but they
have not happened through a ritualized
process in a large group so and i know
some of these experiences have taken
years 12 14 years for some of these
people to actually get to the sense that
there is a different capacity so i don't
want to you know over privilege my
skepticism because i have not done done
the work and so these people that are
doing the work you were asking me this
the other day they're interested for
some reason in coming together yeah to
the home territory of somewhat skeptic
right right to do the work together
which is a performance of the root
theory in their practice because there
will be different versions perspectival
versions of what exactly is going on
in an opportunity to see if that can be
moved to the words get tricky because no
one no one's saying things move to a
collective agreement because as soon as
it becomes in the experience becomes
back into the terms and you have
perspectival multiplicity falls out
again so you can't capture it with some
of these other terms and and then
languaging that is interesting to me so
so that's that's kind of my preamble
about about this yeah there's a lot a
lot of ground to cover but you can hear
the skepticism in the way I'm careful to
I'm not a negative 'used you know um but
I'm like an Iowan you know you gotta
show me show me um so yeah that's that's
that's where I'm at and I hope I didn't
scare anyone away from coming to the
symposium with happened to hear this I
kind of I can't imagine how you would
have I I don't have that much experience
with it like or with its whatever they
are and so I would only be speaking from
very limited experience and then
conjecture and hypothetical distinctions
I don't know if that would be valuable
huh yeah I think that um
I think it would be valuable I think we
could talk around it and and use that as
a little journey into what either what
the obstacles are or what the potential
pitfalls are you know I think that that
I was talking to someone the other day a
mutual friend of ours and you know we
were we were agreeing that some of this
is typology so if you tend to be more of
an individualist than this is not
necessarily going to be the way you are
going to you're going to experience that
that differently but those are some of
the distinctions that I would make okay
so mmm you made a distinction earlier
which I was like very interested in you
use the word mass consciousness to
describe a subtle energy field that
happens in groups and I'm wondering and
I'm not saying that there's one thing
called collective insight or that you
know all these different leaders of
group processes are tapping into the
same thing even tapping into I don't
even know what language to use yet
because I right it sucks yeah there's
different ways of characterizing what's
happening here and what's happened that
many different things might be happening
but I'm wondering why you think that
kind what you said is mass consciousness
first of all what's that and why is that
not what these people are doing right so
that would be I'm certainly not accusing
any of these people of doing that and
that's the far end of what nobody wants
to be doing but there is an experience
that people and groups can have I would
call it an a subtle energy experience I
mean you walk into a funeral home and
it'll hit you right so what is that
that's a transmission of a subtle energy
it with a certain emotional content and
or you can be
I remember the Vancouver riots and
people describing how hard it was to be
on the periphery because the energy
itself moves the patterns of energy in
you and so you can find yourself
becoming more violent and more
aggressive or more in that that that
experience so so there's a and why is
that not what's happening how are you
queer that that's not what's happening
in these groups well I'm not clear but
um well there's a dirt there's a kind of
derogatory way of talking about that
mass consciousness you're sort of saying
that they don't want to be doing that
right because because well I think that
this is this is not emergent thing I
mean subtle energy transmission is
nothing new right and so there are
people that in certain places that I've
experienced where you know you can you
can develop a subtle energy field and
then you can prime that with an object
for the conceptual mind so this is the
which you know this is this is your dead
one coming in you can feel it you can
feel your changing you can feel your
heart racing you can feel it can't you
and you have to say yes and then you can
prime that with an object and then you
can align people around the object so
then those two things get entangled and
then forever people can chase the object
and that's easier because they'll chase
the object all the way to the bank or
whatever right so this is not
extraordinary this is and it can be even
maudlin you know I mean people go to
business sales techniques to learn this
people go to become ll NLP practitioners
to learn how to be better salespeople so
now I think it's an interesting
phenomenon and that could be interesting
but it's not what has the possibility of
being something that gives us
a greater capacity evolutionary capacity
or however people they don't usually use
that term but we can use that that term
and it has as many drawbacks at this
point history as it does in you know at
usefulness so I think that that's one
kind of really primitive thing and I'm
not saying that that's not valuable it's
just not not new so what I was pleased
to see in the last couple of experiences
I have is an awareness that we're not
looking for some common denominator
we're looking to be unique in as unique
as we can be and in that process there
is some kind of collective we could call
it a collective state experienced it
will just use that as a placeholder it's
call different things and so this
attention to the uniqueness and I'll
give you an example I I teach this thing
with horses so I do so I'm going to say
that there is a subtle energy aspect of
it but that subtle energy aspect is that
when you're working with horses and you
have you go through this process where
you're bonded with them and you want and
you can't see the horse the horse is
behind you and you want the horse to
stay with you we may have talked about
this the other day but and the horses
behind you if you if you think of the
horse behind you the horse will stay
right there it actually feels stuck back
there because you're actually thinking
of the horse behind you but if you scan
your own body for that place where you
just want the horse to be with you that
that feeling of wanting to be with the
horse or being in relationship doors any
and if you skin it as it rises in your
body the horse will walk along with you
because the uniqueness comes the unique
aspect is is that it comes up as you
whereas in something and these other
experiences you really feel that there's
something in the room or some some
something exterior to you that is
arising and to me that's the baiting the
objective thought you know the mind the
mind wants to see an object out there
and so of course it's a back and forth
and so the the groups that emphasize
that the way the transpersonal arises is
in the unique expression that to me is a
new quality of this work so that would
be one quality that I would I would look
for okay so okay so I have had this
question about whether these one of
these experiences are new or not on one
of the I think it was one of them to
beyond awakening calls between Terry and
Thomas hooble either Terry or Thomas
brought up but whoever brought it up the
only one agreed pre shirt brought up
even like soldiers marching in lockstep
as an example of and then feeling like
they slip into a kind of group
consciousness
as an example of this kind of we space
and in the context of Thomas's worked in
that sense but and so I think
differentiations are good because at
least in terms of there may be different
kinds of experiences but I'm not sure
that that everyone working in these
working in the group spaces are making
distinctions they may want it to be new
or might want their might so i'm not
sure i'm not i'm not so confident that
it's brand new or its old or something
what might be new is ways of getting
into it ways of paying attention to it
while it's happening and then speaking
speaking speaking to it and speaking
from it which makes it stronger and then
potentially utilizing it for a given
purpose consciously within a group right
so so the metaphor of soldiers walking
in step is what I would be against in
other words and so why does that matter
I think it matters because there's
something tricky I call tricky about
post-war humanism and certainly coming
out of World War two where people really
wanted not to be fighting each other
anymore especially Europe and although
Americans the Anglo Americans were came
out of World War two actually quite
individualistic but in Europe and the
whole humanist movement in post-war
humanist movement is primarily a
continental movement and so so that's a
kind of sentiment this this this this
shared consciousness movement has arisen
out of that you know we talked about as
being green and spiral dynamics and in
and the thing is that's nice but
paradoxically it has really it's the
structure of conscious that that best
plays into neoliberal capitalism because
because in the graphics I use is this so
the post-war humanists like to use the
peer-to-peer people like to use this
thing this illustration where you know
there's the big fish eating the little
fish right then what they do is they
take all the little fish and the little
fish are aligned so they're bigger than
the big fish and then they come to eat
the big fish so I say but there is no
big fish who's the big fish capitalism
will whose capital is just a bunch of
people who are aligned there is no big
fish the big fish is a conceptual
illusion right there's only little
fishes right there's only people so the
alignment policy is as problematic as it
has potential and so that's a false
argument and and what's happened you
know Roy Bosch car talks about
capitalism is only able to be maintained
by the creativity of the slaves and
that's what I think has happened you
know so the biggest the biggest boom to
post-war to neo global capitalism is
post-war humanism and you you may or may
not think that's problematic but the
paradox is most for post-war humanists
thinks the biggest problem is capitalism
so there's there's some kind of strange
Oh be careful what you wish for here oh
well um so so if that's the outcome even
if it's not the goal if it's the outcome
of this work then I would say it's
problematic and it certainly would be
unfortunate for someone like Terry
patents work because he truly wants to
move
in two movements that were inspired like
occupy in two movements that will break
down the structures of neoliberal
capitalism and these other types of
status boundaries so so I think his
intention is in the right place but the
question is whether the outcome he's
proposing is actually an effective um
you know counter terrorist attack there
some look you know um if capitalism is
the terrorists here so so for me it
matters and um and yeah and in fact but
the three people I know or the three or
four people i know most well our are
truly undoubtedly not for neoliberal
capitalism or that whole kind of thing
so so there's a so that's one whole
arena like I said I'm speaking from
conjecture so there are questions I have
about these kinds of experiences that I
don't really know so for example like
for example with Thomas people's work he
talks about mmm now see I feel I feel
very uncomfortable referencing any of
these people that I have such little
experience with is leaving him as a
placeholder and we're basically talking
about your understanding we could even
say us our projection we don't care we
can you can use yeah my term i'm just
i'm here i'm curious about i'm curious
i'm very curious about I think it's fun
like right now when I enter enter when I
enter any space and that I think it's
also exciting like there's something and
that's why I don't really want to
separate it so clearly yet from these
from mass consciousness experiences like
it's fun so I what I want to go to up in
my head so like okay the first thing
that's fun to do I think there's lots of
it okay i think that there's lots of
reasons why collective i'm gonna i'm
gonna call it collective consciousness
as a whole okay generally right now come
in in the kind of spiritual circles that
i know of and you know more of this all
these sorts of people doing this kind of
collective work I think there's multiple
reasons why it's interesting but one
basic reason is because it's fun you get
together with a group of people you get
to like so and something very cool
happens between you and there's a sense
of mystery and I don't think I think
energy is very very central to it
because it feels good it can feel juicy
I can feel kind of like you're walking
down a pathway and like you're exploring
a landscape that you've never known
before you can actually feel like
synchronicities become very very
prominent in the space and not just and
it'll feel like not just like even like
I've had experiences in a group where
synchronicities don't just feel in the
members of the group but they also feel
like they're happening with the group
from out from external objects at the
same time and communication becomes
really subtle so it becomes like and if
you're paying attention to it can be a
kind of very neat confirmation of
psychic communication or sublingual
communication so and and it feels good
to be part of a group you know and it
seems like in a lot of cases spontaneity
is a big is a big see again I don't know
the methods all that well but I know at
least in some cases spontaneity and
saying yes to whatever's coming through
you is like a big part of the method and
acting spontaneously improv spontaneous
speech all of these things kind of I
think pretty sure of heard interesting
studies about how they they it can
change where language come
from in your brain so it doesn't feel so
much like I'm thinking about this sort
of thing but and so that just that
experience spontaneity spontaneous
action and speech in general I think
feels good so you know plus it feels
good to be part of a group so all I have
all these questions about basically
what's going on here and then the last
interesting thing is that it can be it
can be it's really exciting to sort of
like see how this could be used to solve
problems basically and that's where
that's where I'm most that's where I
think the sort of like rubber hits the
road I I think what is right there it's
like when you're in when you're with
these people are you how what kinds of
problems can you solve better and is it
truly that you have access to
information and that you wouldn't have
had access to as individuals even
individuals working wonderfully together
and because otherwise it's I mean the
experiences are wonderful and they can
teach us about ourselves and about
groups and about energies and all kinds
of things but but and they're fun so I'm
not counting them but like if they're
really if it really is something new
happening something you know like kind
of like like like paradigm shifting or
something like that then it's got to be
it's got to be like yeah there's
actually new information involvement or
new problems that are solved better
Magnus and and I haven't heard anyone
flat out say yes we're doing something
like that in a really clear way yeah in
a really impressive way also okay hold
on edit breaks you could that storm is
coming so it's very dark outside that's
awesome I'm you sound like you have
great weather there I know did you see
how bright it was when I
started and now it's like it won't
change so fast summer east coast weather
that's so cool I miss it well cuz it's
the transition you know there's not half
hours later ok so now you see so I was
the dour person but this exactly where
my my natural sense of this is exactly
what you're saying what you're saying I
was writing copy for the campaign and I
wrote something about insight or
collective insight you know it's natural
it's spontaneous it's play its
imaginative these are the words that I
would use for this work you know it it
um it's embodied it's I think it's the
collective version of you know what what
we call flow in sports or flow in I
don't know how to say his name but the
person who created that concept and he
uses the same same words you know
there's there's a lot of creativity and
spontaneity in it I like to think of it
it can get at the level where it's like
high play you know like like the even
the conceptual aspects are really moving
in territories that they really haven't
been before but because there's so much
intersubjective resonance that you're
following concepts into new territory
without a lot of experience behind them
you don't have to have gone through a
whole lot of time with someone and you
can start tracking each other in this in
this other way but I would not call that
I you know it says doesn't have that
much to do with what is traditionally
called awakening or anything I mean
it reminds me more of you know those
videos will you see the two kids
sometimes they're twins and they're like
dancing and they're talking and they're
taught their their their words don't
have any concrete signifiers right but
they're tracking each other because they
are together in this other kind of field
right and so so so for me these are
natural primitives you know of human
nature and if we can stay in that and
then add the conceptual blending then
maybe the concepts can create the
insights and the concepts you know but
but but to me that's more like we're
covering something originally and a more
of a process of subtracting then some
kind of new evolutionary territory so I
would say bring you know you know so
that that is another way that I'm more
comfortable with the saying that that is
exactly what on rare occasion we
experience and those of us who know how
to play with people get to experience
that more often and so what has to be
subtracted a lot of things and not
normally have to be subtracted in a work
situation all the power structures have
to be subtracted you never get to that
point of play right so in income there's
a lot of conventional situations where
teams can't really get to that point of
play because of these structures or you
know there's there's all kinds of
obstacles that disabled people from
being spontaneous creative and playful
so you know Harry that's all there is to
it ya know I don't know I and I'm not I
think it's like an awesome explain I
guess yeah you know why why am I why do
I feel skeptical I feel skeptical and
because in some ways it feels like a fad
and I don't really I'm not often on the
forefront of fads and so I feel
resentful what all the cool people are
doing yeah so like you go do it and you
bring it you tell me but yeah I mean it
could be like it could be a whole new
way of being a committed a whole new
thing I mean one thing I'm yeah okay so
one thing is like you know Tom's people
talk to us about but I just don't I'm i
have i have confusions about yeah i mean
so like Thomas whoville talks about not
knowing he talks about speaking from
like a murder I don't know what he's
speaking from emergence but basically
not sure not knowing what you're going
to say next okay and you know it just
feels better it just feels
better to interact with people from that
place even when you're just having a
conversation with a friend like when I'm
in that place or more in that place than
trying to you know repeat old thoughts
that I've had or something like that I
am it's just more fun it's more
spontaneous it's it's more fun um and I
contrast that so like if we were to just
sit together and be like neither knows
where we're gonna go at all we have no
topics in mind we're just gonna we're
just gonna just be here and speak and
see what happens on the total other side
of the spectrum I I point to like a lot
of what my schooling has been like where
the teachers standing in front of the
room and there's a bunch of students
over here and he knows exactly what
gonna say and when he or EP goes to a
conference he knows exactly what he's
going to say he's like there's
information delivery right and it's all
and so it's dead it totally dead and
that's why i hated school even college I
mean that's not you know so so but I do
have a question about and and so it
feels like from the spontaneous place
that new things are happening and it's
not that concepts don't get weaved in
because they're I've learned them
they're part of who I am but I wouldn't
have known those concepts this is my
hypothesis at the moment I'm not sure I
would have known those concepts unless i
received them in an intact way it from
someone else i read them in a book or
something so I get a little concerned
about you know thinking that these
collective consciousness or things are
going to take are going to be like a
huge new thing in a way that we diminish
the value of these not as fun but
potentially use but useful clearly other
ways of communicating in which we're
just delivering information for example
or collecting information or or whatever
you know so so then you know so that's
another that's just another question I
have and it's boring like I feel like
kind of like this then like I feel sort
of like this boring moderate when I say
something like that but like it's like
kind of like common sense kind of thing
but like it's true it's like you know
there's a utility there are utilities to
these different ways of communicating
and I think we're you know on we should
honor the utility of different ways of
all kinds of ways of communicating if we
indeed find that we need that so and the
end and there's more there there's
there's more like a hyper emphasis on
the new you know kind of like
generational disinterest in history
lineage past knowledge I think are bad
for us
you know so there's a lot of themes here
I think the better at play that make me
both excited and slightly hesitant about
that all of this collective
consciousness work yeah I mean I think a
nice attitude is is to be experimental
like you said you know if your
experimental it's always interesting and
and it can often be fun but so so let me
try to make the case for what could
conceivably be useful about it okay so I
was talking to someone the other day and
I use this metaphor and I and I said we
when people usually get together as a
group and we're not talking about people
get together to only do group
consciousness work we're talking about
people who come together to do things
like work out the terms for Syria to
turn over their chemicals or people who
come together to stop the bleeding of
some kind of financial problem in a
large corporate you know now wicked
problems so you get groups come together
and um the initial phase is somewhat
ruled by implicit rules somewhat um then
in what what usually happens is people
or this group that I'm working with let
me just this will make it more easy to
describe I'll just described the
dynamics in this group so there's a
diversity of opinions about building
this
network for building trust at a distance
and there's a pretty strong fault line
between one person which more pragmatic
and object-oriented and one person who
thinks that we have to get the
intellectual design of it right first a
pragmatic person here and you have the
person who's more of a meta thinker now
from where I look at they're both going
to build the same thing but the dynamics
get such that there's a fault line and
then the group involved are are either
you know so then they start adding
people to their team and consciously or
unconsciously it teeters and tatars some
more people get added that on this fault
line is and so some people get in so you
have this polarization thing that's
going to happen that won't go away which
will destroy their ability to make a
system that they want to build it will
please have that fault one so when you
try to talk to people about it what
happens is they just keep downloading
their information in various ways they
just try to argue their point the same
way over and over and over again and
they don't make any progress so I so the
metaphor I use is I like look guys you
know you wouldn't go to a barbecue let's
say everybody came to a group BBQ and
y'all brought your own piece of me so
you brought chicken and you brought ribs
said you wouldn't expect to leave the
barbecue with Uncle chickens and ribs
you'd expect to cook it into something
else you know and so the when you have
people who trust each other but there's
a fault line then the only way to move
is not this one moved to this person's
or this you have to create something
that you never thought of before to me
that's the exciting part like the
the exciting part is that this has gone
on so long that that we know that the
real place we want to be is neither
place I mean you both just dump
everything you know to me that's
unknowing maybe that you was talking
about because we're not making any
movement maybe it's not even progress
maybe at this point even going backwards
is better than not making any movement
and so with that in mind that's what i
would call collective inciting so now
you've all agreed you put it all on the
table and what you're looking at
everything that everyone can see you
agree is not what you want to see it's
not the point it's dead it's known it's
done with now what cook up right oh no
it doesn't exist and so to me that's
very fun and very playful and when that
process happens there is a chance and it
doesn't happen often that people you
have to get creative and crazy and you
come up with different ideas you talk
about things that aren't possible then
all of a sudden some idea wait a second
do you mean this and maybe it's not even
what you meant but that person actually
set it in a way you wish to I said it
and then all of a sudden you don't know
who said what first and you can't really
credit any one person and a lot of times
there's a lot of joy and you laugh but
but something that really nobody to talk
about before never really thought of it
that way before gets generated in this
process and then I would call that
collective inciting and I think it only
requires an orientation around really
understanding that what you know what
you question and what you fear you all
look at it you all look at what all of
its brought to the table and then you
agree what we want to leave with is
none of that look that's it you guys are
out of here that's boring that's dead I
get back to the office I might use it
but for this experience get that out of
here it's no fun mm-hmm so the only
difference I see between that kind of
work when you're describing or it sounds
like you are facilitating that with
people who aren't familiar with it and
these other what these other groups are
doing some of them at least is that
there's a tension being placed on the
field itself on the field or on what the
group is doing itself with an awareness
that this kind of field or space again
don't have the right terms can be
created and is useful so that you
modulate how you're being with each
other moment to moment and how you're in
order to and have attention on the space
itself in order to keep growing the to
keep growing the space which adds an
extra level of excitement to it and
sense of potential I mean what they're
doing I think what they're doing is like
like really it's more like experimental
or theoretical physics you know they're
really looking at what are the
components of what are the qualities
textures tastes components structures
obstacles when people get together and
so for my symposium I'd like to do is
like so now what are just some
principles that we can use to you know
you don't want it you don't want to use
it as a methodology want to prime the
notion of collective consciousness or
anything right we want to or I would
when I use the term collective inciting
I'm not saying this is what other people
are interested in but and it may or may
not lead to more or less a feeling
collective consciousness I'm not sure
I'm not sure you know I've never tried
it with I've never been successful yet
with a naive teen because they usually
just even still argue that that's a good
way Ellen clueless that online course
there have been there's been quite a lot
of movement toward that kind of
discourse that's more more generative
and I think the sense of losing track of
who's who said what first or who had
that idea or how the idea came I think
that's part of that that extent that
feeling you know you don't you don't
yeah so so in a classroom situation we
have a real teacher it feels like that
you know you're talking to the teacher
and and knowledge is being generated but
you stopped to lose track of who's
teaching home it's just kind of yeah
Little Lulu
when I
it feels you know what it feels like it
feels like when i first started
meditating the very first experience i
had of meditating i I this is this is
the excite this is the feeling of
excitement and potential and it doesn't
mean this is my hesitancy with the group
conscience thing it could be really and
I know when I want to support the this
experimentation but I don't think just
the I don't think the feeling of
excitement and potential guarantees
anything I think it just makes it worth
it because like when i first started i
also had yeah okay at first when i first
started meditating i had the experience
of dropping into this whole inner
landscape that i didn't know was there
and it was all i had was textures and
shapes and it was beautiful it was it
was beautiful but and eventually the
novelty of exploring new textures and
shapes itself more off and so that kind
of excitement and potential was no
longer was no longer there really and so
then this there is more of a sense of
like okay well it's time to get down to
work basically it's time to focus on
common sense again and eventually you
know shadow work and integration and
awakening in the context of the ordinary
and so it's it's neat it's neat but but
I'm not I have no I have no no feeling
of you know like oh this is the big
solution to all of our problems I'm
skeptical of any anytime somebody sets
this is the big solution to all of our
problems because because i often find
the most authentic virtues my experience
of the most authentic virtues are that
they feel ground
it like they feel like they come from a
deep place of alcohol deep common sense
those are the people who I really see
like paying attention to the details of
what's going on in the world and just
doing the day-to-day work doing the
day-to-day work to make change happen
and those are the people that make it
possible for visionaries of all sorts to
do experimental work in all directions
and develop new tools for us as a human
race but then it seems to come back to
utilizing those tools in a way that it's
just like yeah step kind of like very
simple very simple unpretentious um you
know grab did yeah I think that that for
me it's more like the subtractive path
right so you have to so if i subtract
the boundary between me my role as a
teacher and your role as a student then
we haven't invented anything new we've
just subtracted something you know and
and that's you know it's a metaphor but
I think that we're always doing kind of
funny things as humans you know we're
always creating prisons we were talking
with this last time and then forgetting
we created them and then we bust out of
them will get so proud of ourselves you
know so like we create the ego and then
we spend two thousand years creating
practices that can deconstruct the ego
and then we get really proud of
ourselves right foot but so this is a
tendency that might happen with this
collective version of is we create this
structure called the wii space and then
it becomes
like completely now that we got rid of
the ego we can create this thing called
the wii space that we all can be
underneath which is really exciting and
then in the next phase we can
deconstruct it and deliberate it again
into our individual selfness and
uniqueness right so I think that's all
fine if it's completely transparent
because it's just creative it's when
it's not transparent that it becomes
painful I would say I mean other than
that you know so so like yeah so I think
that that this is and then the other
thing is i agree with you i think many
of the things that we think are new new
newly arising phenomenon because we're
humans are actually structures or or
types of phenomenon that we inherit from
you know more of our animal nature more
of just being a living adapting organism
more of some more grounded or deeper
levels and and if you start to think of
experiences as striated like that the
quote you know would be an interesting
question as to than what is uniquely
human because i agree with you i think
that the the groundedness that's enter
the subtle energy that we're all on the
same kind of subtle energy flow you can
feel that while porous to it and stuff
that we have we share with you know all
the other sentient beings so it's not
uniquely human and in that sense it's
it's not new
mm-hmm mom but it's rich in it you know
so um i'd like to tell a story about hey
bonita yeah i'll need to go in like five
minutes okay sucka me and with this
story yeah do you ever read the story
Jonathan Livingston Seagull you too yeah
I did oh you did did see that was a big
story for me when we were growing up
because when we were going up in typical
you know American suburbs or rural is
then I went to Catholic school we didn't
feel that individual you know it was
kids of the 50s we felt like things were
kind of the same you know Cirie Jonathan
Livingston Seagull what is he he he like
I'm unique I'm like an individual right
and it's like it's a spiritual
experience so now generations later we
have people going like raw one and it's
a spiritual experience because it's not
orden it's not the usual it's more rare
right it's the same it's the same thing
it's just that all of a sudden you
realize the other side of the coin and
it and you're like whoa whoa one you
know so and that's so that's why for me
it's this like what's new what I like to
play with is being outside of those flip
flop things for the rest of our human
existence getting beyond the duality of
how we organize experience as one or the
other you know so the we thing has a
little bit of that potential trap you
know
and and yet it's still inviting oh yeah
maybe because it's a potential shot we
gotta figure that one out too so now
maybe if people see this last part of
the talk maybe they'll be shall i come
to be inside in the treat I'm not sure
all right this is great it's a great
conversation okay well so that was
helpful I you know you didn't yet I was
I thought you were going to stick up
more for the new consciousness movement
and then we could have had more of a
fight but uh didn't happen that way